Lola Maverick Lloyd Papers, 1903-1952
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Lola Maverick Lloyd papers
1903-1952
Lloyd, Lola Maverick, 1875-1944
MS 94
1 box (.25 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Pacifist; Suffragist; Women's rights activist. A small collection documenting her peace-related activities, during and after World War I, through correspondence and published pamphlets, newsletters, and clippings.
Pacifist; Suffragist; Women's rights activist. Lola Maverick was born 24 November 1875, daughter of George Madison Maverick and Mary Elizabeth Vance; grew up in St. Louis and on the cattle ranch owned by her family; graduated from Smith College, 1897; taught mathematics there, 1901. Married William Bross Lloyd, 1902, son of social reformer, Henry Demarest Lloyd, settling in Winnetka, a wealthy Chicago suburb; divorced, 1916; four children: Mary, William Jr., Georgia, and Jessie. She was a pioneer suffragist; a pacifist; and co- founder, with Jane Addams, of the Woman's Peace Party, 1915. She was a delegate to the International Congress of Women at the Hague, 1915; sailed on Henry Ford's Peace Ship, 1915; co-chaired, with Rosika Schwimmer, the Campaign for World Government; and co-founded the Women's International League for Peace and Freedom. Lloyd was also a painter and studied modeling in Paris, 1931-32. She designed the Texas State House and executed the details. Lola Maverick Lloyd died 25 July 1944.
This small collection of Lola Maverick Lloyd's papers documents her peace-related activities, during and after World War I, through correspondence, unpublished and published writings by Maverick Lloyd and others, biographical materials, periodicals, pamphlets, newsletters, and clippings. Organizations represented include the Women's International League for Peace and Freedom and the Campaign for World Government. There is also one file on her daughter, Jessie Lloyd O'Connor, containing writings, correspondence and printed material.
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection without any additional restrictions.
Addams, Jane, 1860-1935; Lloyd, Lola Maverick, 1875-1944; O'Connor, Jessie Lloyd, 1904-; Feminists--United States--Biography--Sources; Peace movements--United States--History--Sources; Women and peace--History--20th century-Sources
There is related material in the Jessie Lloyd O'Connor Papers and the Schwimmer-Lloyd Collection in the SSC. The bulk of the Maverick Lloyd's Papers can be found at the New York Public Library. Additional papers are at the Swarthmore Peace Collection.
- Contents list (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Peace expedition: article and pamphlet, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Peace literature (various organizations including Women's International League for Peace and Freedom): fliers, pamphlets, writings, minutes (WILPF), and legal documents, 1915-38, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Memorial for LML: typescripts of memorial meeting, articles, and clipping, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Writings by Lola Maverick Lloyd: pamphlets, articles, typescripts, and notes, 1914-43 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Pictures: photographs, postcards, and clippings, 1916-37, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - From LML (drafts), 1910-1938, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - To LML from Mattie Brown Fincke, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Campaign for World Government: printed materials, 1938-52, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)